<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<exam xmlns="https://vpt1.org"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://vpt1.org questions.xsd">
    <head>
        <title>Question Catalog: Personal Mobile Networks</title>
        <version>1.0</version>
        <id>990</id>
    </head>
    <body>
        <!-- Tutorial 1: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="0">
            <body>What are the issues which affect the decision between setting up a wired network or a wireless
                network?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Cost, Ease of Deployment, Scalability, and Flexibility.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">cost</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">deployment</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">scalability</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">flexibility</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="1">
            <body>What are some advantages of wireless networks?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Mobility, Ease of deployment, Reduced Cost-of-Ownership, Scalability, and Flexibility.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">mobility</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">ease of deployment</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">reduced cost-of-ownership</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">scalability</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">flexibility</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="2">
            <body>What are some disadvantages of wireless networks?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Setup and Configuration, Stability, Security, and Speed.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">setup and configuration</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">stability</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">security</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">speed</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="3">
            <body>List and discuss 3 aspects/areas of personal mobile communication impacted by mobility.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Mobile Devices: Lighter, more robust, constrained by battery; Network Protocols: Change in
                        name, address, location, etc.; Security: Endpoint authentication is harder; Performance: Network
                        is slower and delay and jitter are increased; Operation: Need software resources to track and
                        manage devices; Applications: Need to deal with changes in connectivity and QoS;
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">mobile devices</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">network protocol</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">security</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">performance</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">operation</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">application</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="4">
            <body>What is the Hidden Node Problem and how is it solved?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>When two nodes that are invisible to each other communicate with a third node, their
                        transmissions interfere, as they can not sense the carrier. Handshaking using RTS/CTS (Request
                        to Send/Clear to Send) is implemented in conjunction with the CSMA/CA to overcome this problem.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">invisible</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">interfere</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">RTS/CTS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">CSMA/CA</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="5">
            <body>What is the Exposed Node Problem and how is it solved?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>When a node is transmitting to another node and a third node wants to transmit to a fourth
                        one, the third node may falsely believe that it can not do so because it would cause
                        interference. In reality the second node might be outside of transmission range of node three
                        and the fourth node out of transmission range of node one. RTS/CTS messages may be used to
                        overcome this problem under certain circumstances.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">false</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">interfere</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">outside</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">RTS/CTS</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>

        <!-- Tutorial 2: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="14">
            <body>List 3 impairments to wireless signal propagation and explain how each impairment can be alleviated.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Attenuation and Attenuation Distortion: Adaptive equalizer; Free Space Loss: Boost signal
                        strength; Multipath Propagation: Forward error correction;
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">Attenuation and Attenuation Distortion</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Free Space Loss</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Multipath Propagation</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="15">
            <body>List 3 common sources of noise in wireless communication systems and explain their causes.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Thermal noise: Function of temperature; Intermodulation noise: Occurs if signals with
                        different frequencies share the same medium; Crosstalk: One circuit accidentally picks up
                        signals in another
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">thermal</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">intermodulation</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">crosstalk</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="16">
            <body>What are the 2 common algorithms used in an adaptive filter to derive the optimum weights of the
                filter? State the cost functions used by the 2 algorithms to minimize the error signal.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Least Mean Squares (LMS) and Recursive Least Square (RLS).</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">least mean square</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">recursive least square</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="17">
            <body>What are the 3 common important signal propagation mechanisms that result in multipath propagation of
                wireless signals?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Reflection, Diffraction, and Scattering.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">reflection</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">diffraction</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">scattering</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="18">
            <body>What are the characteristics of a Rayleigh fading channel?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Large number of multipath signals with no dominant signal along line-of-sight.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">multipath</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">no dominant</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="19">
            <body>What are the characteristics of a Rician fading channel?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Large number of multipath signals with a dominant signal.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">multipath</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">dominant</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="20">
            <body>What are the 2 basic properties that determine the quality of digitized speech signal?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Sampling rate and bit depth.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">sampling rate</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">bit rate</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <!-- not complete -->

        <!-- Tutorial 3: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="30">
            <body>List and briefly explain the 3 basic types of digital modulation.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Amplitude (ASK), Frequency (FSK), Phase (PSK) Shift Keying</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">amplitude</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">frequency</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">phase</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="31">
            <body>What are the 2 transmission techniques used?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Narrow‐band transmission: Each signal transmits on one radio frequency, or a very narrow range
                        of frequencies; Spread spectrum transmission: Transmitter takes a narrow band signal and spreads
                        it over a broader portion of the radio frequency band
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">narrow-band</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">spread spectrum</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="32">
            <body>What are the 2 common spread spectrum techniques used? Briefly explain their operations.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Frequency Hopping Spread Spectrum (FHSS): Use a range of frequencies and change frequency
                        multiple times during transmission; Direct Sequence Spread Spectrum (DSSS): Uses an expanded
                        redundant code to encode each data bit before transmitting
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">frequency hopping spread spectrum</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">direct sequence spread spectrum</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="33">
            <body>What are the 3 most common techniques adopted to support multiple access in wireless communication?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Frequency Division Multiple Access (FDMA), Time Division Multiple Access (TDMA), and Code
                        Division Multiple Access (CDMA)
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">Frequency Division Multiple Access</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Time Division Multiple Access</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Code Division Multiple Access</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="34">
            <body>FDMA is susceptible to crosstalk. Suggest a common mechanism to reduce crosstalk. What is the
                disadvantage of using this mechanism.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Special guard band frequencies are used to prevent the frequencies from “bleeding” over one
                        another. This reduces usable bandwidth.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">guard band</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">reduce</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">bandwidth</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>

        <!-- Tutorial 4: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="35">
            <body>How many active master device(s) and active slave device(s) can be supported in a Bluetooth piconet?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>1 active master and 7 active slaves.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">1</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">7</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="36">
            <body>Bluetooth slave devices can communicate with one another directly. Is this statement true or false?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>False. Slave devices can only communicate with the master.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">False</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="37">
            <body>How does Bluetooth enable all devices in a Piconet to communicate without interference and to allow
                them to share the channel?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>It uses FHSS to allow devices to communicate without interference and TDD-TDMA to share the
                        channel.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">FHSS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">TDD-TDMA</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="38">
            <body>Explain how a Bluetooth device performs the discovery of the other Bluetooth devices within its
                range.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Inquiry and Page from the Inquiring Device, Inquiry and Page Scan from the other devices
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">Inquiry</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Page</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Page Scan</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="39">
            <body>With FHSS, explain how the Bluetooth discovery process ensure that the receiver can be discovered
                since they may be using different frequency channels?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Inquiring device inquires using many channels and receivers can issue multiple inquiry
                        responses.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">many channels</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="40">
            <body>Explain why the Bluetooth discovery process can take as long as 10.24s.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Full scan of 32 frequencies (with 128 repetitions) is repeated up to 4 times: 4 * 2,56s.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">32 frequencies</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">128 repetitions</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">4 times</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="41">
            <body>Explain the difference in the operation of a Bluetooth slave device being assigned a 3‐bit Active
                Member Address (AMA) versus one being assigned an 8‐bit Passive Member Address (PMA)!
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Active devices (with AMA) can send and receive data. Parked devices release the AMA and are
                        assigned a PMA. They cannot send data but can listen on a beacon interval.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">send</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="42">
            <body>What is the AMA of the Bluetooth Master? What address is used by the Bluetooth Master to send a
                broadcast message?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Both are 0.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">0</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="43">
            <body>List and explain the 3 power saving modes for Bluetooth devices!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Hold: Master and slave agree on a one‐time HOLD duration after which the slave synchronizes
                        with the channel traffic and data transfer restarts. Slave keeps AMA.; Sniff: Slave listens at a
                        reduced rate and keeps AMA.; Park: Slave looses AMA, gets PMA, and can not send any more.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">hold</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">sniff</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">park</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="44">
            <body>What is the purpose of Bluetooth pairing?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Pairing using PIN is a security mechanism to restrict access to authorised users only.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">security</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="45">
            <body>Explain the digital modulation used by Bluetooth!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>GFSK has a carrier frequency, called the center frequency (fc) and it uses 2 different
                        frequencies to indicate a 1 (higher) or a 0 (lower) being tx.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">center frequency</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="46">
            <body>List and explain the 2 types of links that can be created between the Bluetooth master and slave!
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Syn Connection Oriented (SCO): faster, for real‐time data, max 3 links to 1 master; Asyn
                        Connection‐Less (ACL): slower, best effort transfer, max 1 link to 1 master
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">SCO</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">ACL</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="47">
            <body>What are some of the differences between Standard Bluetooth and Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE)?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>BLE uses Adaptive Frequency Hopping (AFH) and has no limit on the number of slaves. It also
                        features very low-power sleep modes. (AND MORE)
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">AFH</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">number of slaves</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">low-power sleep</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>

        <!-- Tutorial 5: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="48">
            <body>What are two factors that affect the throughput of a user in a WLAN?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Distance from AP; Number of users sharing the aggregate bandwidth of the AP</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">distance</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">number of users</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="49">
            <body>What are the two general modes for WLAN?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Infrastructure mode and Ad-hoc mode</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">infrastructure</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">ad-hoc</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="50">
            <body>What are characteristics of WLAN in infrastructure mode?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Stations communicate with AP only; AP requires strategic placement; AP connects to wired
                        backbone network
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">communicate with AP</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">strategic placement</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">wired backbone network</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="51">
            <body>What are characteristics of WLAN in ad-hoc mode?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>No fixed connection; Nodes transmit directly to each other; Poor performance as users are
                        spread out
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">no fixed connection</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">transmit directly</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">poor performance</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="52">
            <body>List and briefly explain the services provided by a WLAN stationt!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Authetication: proves identity of one station to another; Deauthentication: removes
                        previously authenticated station; Privacy: prevents messages from being read by unintended
                        recipient; Data Delivery: provides reliable delivery from MAC of one station to MAC of other
                        stations
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">authentication</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">deauthentication</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">privacy</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">data delivery</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="53">
            <body>List and briefly explain the services provided by a WLAN Access Point!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Association: makes logical connection between stations and AP; Disassociation: used to inform
                        AP that station is no longer requiring service; Reassociation: used when station moves to new
                        BSS (new AP); Distribution: determines where to send packets; Integration: allows connection to
                        other wired and wireless LANs
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">association</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">disassociation</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">reassociation</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">distribution</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">integration</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="54">
            <body>List any three general types of Media Access Control!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>TDMA, FDMA, FHSS, DSSS, CDMA, SDMA, and Random Access</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">TDMA</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">FDMA</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">FHSS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">DSSS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">CDMA</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">SDMA</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Random Access</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="55">
            <body>List the two coordination functions used for media access in WLAN and list two characteristics for
                each function.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>
                        DCF (Distributed Coordination Function): For infrastructure and ad-hoc mode, uses CSMA/CA+ACK
                        and contention resolution; PCF(Point Coordination Function): For infrastructure mode only, the
                        AP has to allow a station to send
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">DCF</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">PCF</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="56">
            <body>What is Inter Frame Spacing (IFS) and what is its purpose?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Refers to time interval between two successive frames by any station. Used to reduce collision
                        probability and prioritize different packets.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">interval between two frames</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">reduce collision</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">prioritize</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="57">
            <body>List and explain the 4 IFS used in the basic 802.11 WLAN operation!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>SIFS (Short IFS): Used for immediate response actions (e.g. ACK); PIFS (Point coordination
                        function IFS): Used by centralized controller in PCF scheme; DIFS (Distributed coordination
                        function IFS): Used as minimum delay of asynchronous frames contending for access; EIFS
                        (Extended IFS): Used for resynchronization when PHY detects incorrect MAC frame reception
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">SIFS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">PIFS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">DIFS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">EIFS</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="58">
            <body>List 3 control access techniques in DCF and explain the scenario in which the control access technique
                is most applicable!
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>CSMA/CA+ACK: Error-free channel; RTS/CTS: presence of hidden terminal/ interference;
                        Fragmentation: high number of retransmissions
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">CSMA/CA+ACK</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">RTS/CTS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">fragmentation</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="59">
            <body>What is the function of the Network Allocation Vector (NAV) in 802.11?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>It is used for the implementation of virtual carrier sense that works by specifying the
                        duration of a transmission in the frame header. Stations can copy the duration value into their
                        NAV and count down until the medium is not busy any more. It also helps conserving power by
                        reducing the need for physical carrier sensing.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">virtual carrier sense</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="60">
            <body>Explain what happens when the Contention Period in one superframe (i.e. contention-free repetition
                period) overruns into the next superframe!
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>The CFP is foreshortened.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">foreshorten</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="61">
            <body>Briefly explain how OFDM and MIMO operate!</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing: Divides the wide channel into many subchannels
                        (called subcarriers), Sends part of the message frame in each subcarrier in parallel, Subcarrier
                        tx are redundant; Multiple Input/Multiple Output: Two or more spatial streams can be sent at the
                        same time in the same channel but from different sending antennas, Reveiver uses multipath time
                        differences to distinguish between them
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">orthogonal frequency division multiplexing</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">multiple input/multiple output</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="62">
            <body>What are the advantages of OFDM and MIMO?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>OFDM: Very easy and efficient in dealing with multi‐path, Robust against narrow‐band
                        interference; MIMO: Increases throughput, Robust against multipath fading
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">multipath</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">narrow-band interference</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">throughput</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="63">
            <body>List and briefly explain the techniques used in 802.11n to improve throughput.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>MIMO: up to 4 spatial streams; Channel Bonding: use two separate channels at once; Frame
                        Aggregation: combine small frames to decrease protocol overhead; Utilization of
                        dual‐radio RF band: one radio for 2,5GHz and 5GHz region each
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">mimo</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">channel bonding</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">frame aggregation</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">dual-radio rf band</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="64">
            <body>List and briefly explain the techniques used in 802.11ac to improve throughput.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Beamforming with MIMO: up to 8 spatial streams that are directed towards the target; Channel
                        Bonding: use two separate channels at once; MU-MIMO (Multi-User MIMO): AP can transmit multiple
                        frames to different clients simultaneously on the same frequency spectrum; Denser Modulation:
                        256 QAM
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">beamforming</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">channel bonding</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">mu-mimo</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">denser modulation</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="65">
            <body>What are the 2 coordination functions used in 802.11e?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>EDCF (Enhanced DCF): Station with higher priority traffic waits less to transmit, Used in CP
                        only; HCF (Hybrid coordination function): Combination of DCF and PCF, Uses ECDF in CP, AP
                        controls access in CFP and allocates more timeslots to stations with high-priority traffic
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">enhanced DCF</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">hybrid coordination function</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="66">
            <body>How does HCF gain access to the channel during the Contention Period?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>HC can allocate polled TXOPs (Transmit Opportunity) by issuing QoS CF-Poll after detecting the
                        channel as being idle for PIFS, which is shorter than DIFS. Hence HC has priority.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">QoS CF-Poll</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>

        <!-- Tutorial 6: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="67">
            <body>List 2 characteristics each for Circuit Switching, Packet Switching and Message Switching
                technologies.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Circuit Switching: allocates resources for entire duration of transfer, all data takes the
                        same path; Packet Switching: all data is divided into packets, each packet is routed separately;
                        Message Switching: messages are sent in their entirety, store and forward
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">allocate</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">same path</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">data is divided</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">routed separately</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">entire</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">store and forward</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="68">
            <body>Discuss the advantages and disadvantages of circuit switching technology and packet switching
                technology.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Circuit switching provides low delays, but needs a setup phase and blocks resources during the
                        entire connection time, even if no data is sent. Packet switching provides better line
                        efficiency and is more reliable, but may have higher delays and has jitter.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">low delay</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">setup phase</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">blocks</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">line efficiency</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">reliable</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">jitter</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="69">
            <body>Name and explain the 3 common cellular phone codes used.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>International Mobile Station Equipment Identity (IMEI) or equivalent: Unique and permanent ID
                        programmed into phone; Mobile Identification Number (MIN): 10‐digit # derived from the phone #;
                        System Identification Code (SID): unique 5‐digit # that is assigned to each carrier by the FCC
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">IMEI</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">MIN</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">SID</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="70">
            <body>What is the main design characteristic of cellular networks which allow them to offer high capacity in
                a limited frequency spectrum?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Frequency reuse.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">frequency reuse</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="71">
            <body>Explain how the cellular phone system is able to support frequency reuse.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>BS and cell phones operate at low power. Adjacent cells are assigned different frequencies.
                        Frequencies are reused every few cells.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">low power</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">adjacent</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="72">
            <body>Explain why a cluster size of 1 is not recommended in a cellular system using FDMA.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Too much interference.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">interference</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="73">
            <body>Explain why IS-95 cellular system using CDMA/DSSS can have a frequency reuse factor of 1.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>CDMA allows multiple transmissions on the same frequency.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">CDMA</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="74">
            <body>Explain the difference between handoff and roaming in the context of a cellular phone network.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Handoff means a user is switching cells within a network. Roaming means a user is switching
                        between networks.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">cell</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">network</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="75">
            <body>Explain the difference between hard and soft handoffs.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Hard handoff means cutting communications with one BS before connecting to the new BS, while
                        soft handoff is the opposite.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">BS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">before connecting</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="76">
            <body>Explain why handoff margin cannot be too large or too small.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>If it is too large it will cause unnecessary handoffs and if it is too small calls will be
                        lost before the handoff is complete.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">unnecessary</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">lost</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="77">
            <body>Explain how a call is received on a cell phone.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>The phone registers with cell it has the strongest signal to. This registration is forwarded
                        to the MTSO as well. When a call comes in the MTSO finds the called phone by registration and
                        sets a frequency pair for phone and BS to use. Once the phone accepted the call the MTSO sets up
                        a circuit between calling and called BS as well as traffic channels within the caller and called
                        BS.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">MTSO</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">BS</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">registration</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="78">
            <body>AMPS uses FDMA to divide a 25 MHz band into 30 kHz channels. However, only 832 channels are defined as
                available for use. Explain the use of the 833rd channel.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>It is used as a guard band.</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">guard band</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="79">
            <body>Explain the 2 key factors which allows the 2G and above cellular technologies to increase system
                capacity over 1G cellular technologies.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Efficient use of frequency spectrum and less transmitter power.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">efficient use of frequency spectrum</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">less transmitter power</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="80">
            <body>In GSM, a 25 MHz band is divided into 124 200 kHz physical channels using FDMA. What and where is the
                125th channel used for.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>The last channel is split into two 100 kHz channels. They are guard bands at the beginning and
                        end of the 124 carrier channels.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">split</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">guard band</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="81">
            <body>List 3 advantages of CDMA based cellular phone systems.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Frequency diversity: everyone is allocated the entire frequency spectrum which reduces
                        frequency-dependant transmission impairments; Multipath resistance: chipping codes used for CDMA
                        exhibit low cross correlation and low autocorrelation; Privacy: since signals are noise-like and
                        encoded
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">frequency diversity</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">multipath resistance</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">privacy</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>

        <!-- Tutorial 7: Qualitative Questions -->
        <question type="extended-answer" id="82">
            <body>What are the roles of the Master Ground station in the GPS system?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>The Master Ground station sends orbital data and clock corrections it receives from other
                        ground stations to the satellites. The satellites can then incorporate these updates into the
                        signals they send to GPS receivers.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">send</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">orbital data</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">clock correction</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="83">
            <body>What is the number of satellites needed to compute the location of a GPS user?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>4</body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">4</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="84">
            <body>List and briefly explain the 3 sets of signals transmitted by the GPS space vehicles.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>C/A Code (Coarse Aquisition): modulated onto L1 carrier and can be accessed by everyone; P
                        Code (Precise): modulated onto L1 and L2 carriers and can only be accessed by US military;
                        Navigation Message: contains positional and timing data and health of the satellite
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">C/A Code</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">P Code</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">Navigation Message</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="85">
            <body>Explain how the measurements from the 4th satellite can be used by a GPS receiver to determine a
                correction factor to offset the drift in the receiver’s clock from the satellite clock.
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>The receiver can look for a single correction factor for its timings that would lead to all 4
                        satellites measurements to have one single intersection. This correction brings the Receiver
                        back in sync.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">correction factor</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">single intersection</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="86">
            <body>List and briefly explain 2 methods used for time measurements in GPS receivers.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Carrier phase ranging: phase difference of a received carrier compared to a reference carrier
                        can be used to compute time on arrival; Code phase ranging: phase difference of a received code
                        compared to a reference code can be used to compute time on arrival
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">carrier phase ranging</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">code phase ranging</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="87">
            <body>Which pilot signal(s) is/are used in Standard Positioning Services (SPS) and Precision Positioning
                Services (PPS)?
            </body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>SPS: code phase ranging using spread pilot signal on L1; PPS: code phase ranging using spread
                        pilot signals on L1 and L2
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">L1</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">L1 and L2</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="88">
            <body>List and briefly explain the sources of errors in GPS positioning system.</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>Ionospheric error: ionosphere slows signal propagation; Tropospheric error: troposphere slows
                        signal propagation; Clock and ephemeris errors; Receiver noise; Multipath
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">ionospheric error</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">tropospheric error</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">clock and ephemeris error</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">receiver noise</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">multipath</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="89">
            <body>Explain how satellite alignment affects the Dilution of Precision (DoP).</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>GPS satellites close together lead to a large area of uncertainty when calculating an
                        intersection and hence high DoP.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">area of uncertainty</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">intersection</mark>
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
        <question type="extended-answer" id="90">
            <body>How does Differential GPS improve the accuracy of the location determined?</body>
            <answers>
                <answer>
                    <body>A reference station constantly computes the difference between actual distance and measured
                        distance to all visible satellites. From this difference it computes correction data for each
                        satellite and directly broadcasts it to mobile receivers nearby.
                    </body>
                    <marks>
                        <mark type="keyword">reference station</mark>
                        <mark type="keyword">correction data</mark>´
                    </marks>
                </answer>
            </answers>
        </question>
    </body>
</exam>
